Finding Aid for Women’s Glee Club (University of Michigan) records, 1903-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women's Glee Club (University of Michigan) records 1903-2010 1979-2006
University of Michigan. Women's Glee Club.
2008160 Bimu 2
Singing group established in 1902 as the University of Michigan Girls' Club before changing the name to Women's Glee Club in the 1940s. The group performed on campus and throughout Michigan as well as touring nationally and internationally. The group disbanded in 1953 and was reactivated in 1976. This records include concert programs and posters, fundraising information, correspondence, photographs, audio/visual recordings of performances, newspaper clippings and scrapbooks. Also included are administrative papers including budget information, schedules, rosters and rules.
3 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records have been received in periodic accessions since 1997. Included in this collection are records received in October 1997 and July 2008 (donor # 8652 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Women's Glee Club records are open without restriction.
In the spring of 1902, the University of Michigan Girl's Glee Club was created by the Women's League to provide an opportunity for non-music majors to perform in an organized group. The club was open to both undergraduate and graduate students, and had seventeen members in its first year. By 1905, the club had gained such popularity on campus that Professor Albert A. Stanley appointed fellow School of Music faculty member, Nora Crane Hunt, to direct the club. The women sang on campus, in surrounding Michigan cities, and at Ohio State and Ohio Wesleyan universities. The club's greatest exposure came in the early 1930s when they were chosen to represent the University of Michigan's musical groups on a National Broadcasting Company radio show. The Girl's Glee Club membership grew steadily from around 20 members in 1912, to a high of 70 members in the 1930s.
Former student director Margaret Martindale took over Nora Crane Hunt's post as director when she retired in 1933. Under her direction, the club performed at the May Festival that same year, a performance so admired that the group became known as the "Stanley Chorus," a tribute to the professor who had earlier incorporated the club into the School of Music. The name, however, was short-lived, and the group began to refer to themselves again as the Girl's Glee Club in 1937, only to change their name for good in the 1940s to the Women's Glee Club. During the 1940s boom time the club met in Burton Tower every Thursday evening, and over the next decade the women would hold a couple of performances in Ann Arbor, at least one out-of-town concert, and a few radio broadcasts annually. However, the growing popularity of other newly-formed performance groups, together with dwindling membership following World War II, and the difficulty of finding a suitable conductor all contributed to the disbanding of the Women's Glee Club in 1953. This decision was mutually agreed upon by the Michigan League, Dean of Women Deborah Bacon, and Dean of the School of Music Earl Moore.
In 1976, after 23 years of inactivity, student Kimberley Smith decided the time had come to revive the group to continue the original mission of the Girl's Glee Club to "provide an opportunity for women at the University of Michigan to keep music in their lives." In 1978, Rosalie Edwards took over as director, creating a number of groups within the club: the Madrigal Choir, the a cappella group The Harmonettes, and the spirit club "Bo's Boosters." In 1981, the Women's Glee Club was officially offered as a one-credit course through the School of Music, and in 1994 the School of Music faculty began officially conducting the group. The year 1987 marked their first national tour, taking the 60-plus members to the East Coast through Boston, Washington, D.C., Pittsburgh, New York City and Buffalo. Subsequent tours took them around the Midwest, Southeast and West Coast. The club took their first international tour to the Netherlands, France and England in 2000. In 1995 one of the most successful outreach programs offered by the Women's Glee Club was created, the Women's Vocal Arts Day. This event offered the opportunity for high school girls interested in singing to learn more about performance at the college level. In 2006, the Midnight Blue jazz octet was formed as another subgroup of the growing club.
The Women's Glee Club continues to perform twice a year in their Fall and Spring Concerts, as well as at their "Blues" tailgate performances. In addition to other shows they hold around Ann Arbor and the state of Michigan, they continue their national and international touring tradition.
Sources Consulted:
Wilfred B. Shaw, ed. The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedia Survey. Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan University Press, 1942-1981.
The Women's Glee Club collection dates from 1903 to 2008 and is comprised of two accessions. Because the two accessions came with little discernible structure, and because their contents overlapped, they were combined into one collection made up of printed and manuscript materials, as well as posters, scrapbooks, sound and video recordings in a few different formats. The collection has been divided into four series: Audio/Visual Materials, Topical File, Scrapbooks and Concert Posters. The first two series of the collection have been arranged alphabetically by topic, and chronologically within the files. The Scrapbooks series is contained in Box 2, and each scrapbook has retained its original organization.
Subjects:
Choral singing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. Women's Glee Club.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Choral singing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan. Women's Glee Club.
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; Compact discs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.; Scrapbooks.
- Audio/Visual Materials
  Audio/Visual Materials contain materials from 1986 to 2007, and include five VHS, three audio cassette and one CD recordings of concerts, as well one CD of photos. The photographs contained in this series are both undated and dated material from 1946 to 2008, with the bulk of the dated photographs falling in the 1983-2008 range. These materials are separated into two categories: Performance photos and Social photos. Items of note in the Performance-undated folder are two photographs, one autographed by Congressman Phil Crane and the other autographed by Congressman Carl Purcell.
  - Cassette tape recordings (Box 1)
    - 1994 Spring Concert, 1 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - 1995 Spring Concert, 1 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - 1995 Fall Concert, 1 audiocassettes (Box 1)
  - CD recordings
    - 2001 Fall Concert, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 1)
    - 2002 Spring Concert, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 1)
    - 2002 Winter Concert, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 1)
    - 2003 Winter Concert, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 1)
    - 2004 Spring Concert, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 1)
    - 2004 Winter Concert, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 1)
    - 2006 Concert at First Congregational Church, Ann Arbor, MI, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 1)
  - Data CD
    - 2007 Spring photographs, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Performance
      - 1946-2010 (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
    - Social
      - 1985-2010 (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
  - VHS recordings
    - 1986 Fall Concert, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 1)
    - 1987 Fall Concert, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 1)
    - 1988 Spring Concert, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 1)
    - 1989 Spring Concert, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 1)
    - Undated demo tape, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 1)
- Topical File
  The Topical File contains the basic records of the Women's Glee Club collection from 1948 to 2008, with the bulk of materials falling in the 1979 to 2006 range. The file is arranged in four topics: Administrative (budgets, correspondence, handbooks and schedules, directories and rosters, meeting notes, miscellaneous items, and tour information), Concerts (programs, and tickets), Fundraising, Marketing (alumni newsletters, audition and recruitment posters, and clippings). Of particular interest in the Administrative-Correspondence folder is a copy of a 1990 letter from former president Gerald Ford to then-director Rosalie Edwards.
  - Administrative
    - Budget 1999-2002 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1980-2008 (Box 1)
    - Handbooks and schedules 1994-2008 (Box 1)
    - Directories and rosters 2002-2008 (Box 1)
    - Meeting notes 2004 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Undated (Box 1)
    - Tour information 1995-2008 (Box 1)
  - Concerts
    - Concert Posters 1981-1996, undated
      - 1981 Spring Concert (Box 3)
      - 1983 Spring Concert (Box 3)
      - 1983 Fall Concert (Box 3)
      - 1984 Spring Concert (Box 3)
      - 1986 Spring Concert (Box 3)
      - 1986 Fall Concert (Box 3)
      - 1989 Spring Concert (Box 3)
      - 1992 Fall Concert (Box 3)
      - 1993 Fall Concert (Box 3)
      - 1995 Spring Concert (Box 3)
      - 1995 Fall Concert (Box 3)
      - 1996 Spring Concert (Box 3)
      - undated, 4 posters (Box 3)
    - Programs
      - 1948, 1979-1989 (Box 1)
      - 1990-1999 (Box 1)
      - 2000-2010 (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
    - Tickets 1985-2006 (Box 1)
  - Fundraising
    - 1986-2008 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Marketing
    - Alumni newsletter "Arioso," 2003-2006 (Box 1)
    - Auditions and Recruitment posters
      - 1982, 2007 (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
    - Clippings
      - 1980-1993 (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks contain letters, clippings, programs, posters and sheet music, a few of which can be found organized in the other series. The original organization of the scrapbooks was maintained, with materials dating from 1903 to 2006. There is one oversize scrapbook.
  - 1903-1996, white binder (Box 2)
  - 1929-1987, maroon binder with fleur-de-lis pattern (Box 2)
  - 1940-2006, maroon binder with border (Box 2)
  - 1979-1984, black binder (Box 2)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    (in sheet protector)
  - 1982 (Box 2)
    (stapled packet of paper)
  - 2000-2004 (Volume 1)